<works>
  <work>
    <title>Supporting decision makers in search-based product line architecture design using clustering</title>
    <author>Willian Marques Freire</author>
    <abstract>The Product Line Architecture (PLA) is one of the most important artifacts of a Software Product Line (SPL). 
    PLA design can be formulated as an optimization problem with many factors. In this context, the MOA4PLA approach was 
    proposed to optimize PLA design using search algorithms and metrics specific to the context. 
    MOA4PLA treats the PLA design as a multi-objective optimization problem. At the end of the search process several PLA design 
    alternatives are presented to the decision maker, difficulting the decision about which PLA alternative best fits with 
    his/her needs. In this sense, this work proposes the usage of clustering algorithms to group PLAs design alternatives, 
    according to their characteristics and assist the decision maker in the choice of one PLA design for the SPL. 
    For this purpose, an empirical study was carried out, involving quantitative and qualitative experiments. 
    Such an study integrated the K-Means++ and DBSCAN clustering algorithms in the MOA4PLA approach. 
    The results of the experiments were promising, since an appropriate grouping of the solutions can be quantitatively observed, 
    and also, qualitatively, the suitability of the solutions to the decision makers needs was verified.</abstract>
    <paperlink>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8754394</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8754394</experimentalpackagelink>
  </work>
  <work>
    <title>Towards the support of user preferences in search-based product line architecture design: an exploratory study</title>
    <author>Carlos Vinicius Bindewald</author>
    <abstract>Software Product Lines (SPLs) is a reuse approach in which a family of products is generalized in a 
    common architecture that can be adapted to different clients. The Product Line Architecture (PLA) is one of 
    the most important artifacts of a SPL. PLA design requires great human effort as it involves several factors 
    that are usually in conflict. To ease this task, PLA design can be formulated as an optimization problem with 
    many factors, i.e, as a multi-objective optimization problem. In this context, the MOA4PLA approach was proposed 
    to optimize PLA design using search algorithms and metrics specific to the context. This approach supported by 
    OPLA-Tool has already been used in several works demonstrating its applicability. However, MOA4PLA does not take 
    into account aspects that are subjective, such as the preferences of a particular Decision Maker (DM). To do so, 
    this paper presents a proposal to incorporate the user preferences in the optimization process performed by MOA4PLA,
    through an interactive process in which the DM subjectively evaluates the solutions in processing time. Thus, 
    the solutions generated can be better suited to the DM's needs or preferences. In order to allow the user interaction, 
    modifications were made in MOA4PLA and implemented in the OPLA-Tool. Aiming at an initial validation of the proposal, 
    an exploratory study was carried out, composed of two experiments: a qualitative and a quantitative. These experiments
    were realized with the participation of a software architect. Empirical results pointed out that the proposed interactive
    process enables the generation of PLAs that are in accordance with the architect's preferences. 
    Another significant contribution are the lessons learned on how to improve the interactive process.</abstract>
  </work> 
  <paperlink>https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3351993</paperlink>
  <experimentalpackagelink>https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3351993</experimentalpackagelink>
</works>
