<works>
   <work>
    <year>2019</year>
    <title>Prevention of Architectural Anomalies in Product Line Design Optimization</title>
    <author>Tiago Tadeu Madrigar</author>
    <abstract>The use of search algorithms has been successfully explored in the optimization 
       of Software Product Line Architecture (PLA) design in the seminal approach called 
       Multi-Objective Approach for Product-Line Architecture Design (MOA4PLA). Such an approach 
       produces a set of PLA design alternatives that improves the different optimized factors. 
       In addition to the optimization of these factors, the PLA projects obtained should ideally be 
       free of architectural anomalies. An architectural anomaly can negatively impact both the 
       variability and extensibility of PLA and other non-functional attributes. However, search-based 
       approaches, such as MOA4PLA, adversely introduce architectural anomalies into the automatically 
       generated solutions. Therefore, in the present work, we present the OPLA-Tool-ASP tool, which 
       implements guidelines to prevent the Unused Interface, Unused Brick and Concern Overload anomalies 
       in the context of MOA4PLA. In addition, we investigated the prevention of Link Overload anomaly. 
       A study involving two experiments was conducted in order to analyze the efficiency of these guidelines. 
       The results of this study show that the prevention of the studied architectural anomalies is feasible 
       and that there are points of improvement in relation to the Link Overload anomaly prevention guideline.</abstract>
    <paperlink>http://cibse2020.ppgia.pucpr.br/images/artigos/5/S05_P1.pdf</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink>https://github.com/otimizes/experimental-package-asp</experimentalpackagelink>
  </work>
   <work>
    <year>2020</year>
    <title>Architectural Feature Re-Modularization for Software Product Line Evolution</title>
    <author>Luciane Baldo Nicolodi</author>
    <abstract>Extensive maintenance leads to the Software Product
      Line Architecture (PLA) degradation over time. When there is the need of
evolving the Software Product Line (SPL) to include new features,
or move to a new platform, a degraded PLA requires considerable
effort to understand and modify, demanding expensive refactoring
activity. In the state of the art, search-based algorithms are used to
improve PLA at package level. However, recent studies have shown
that the most variability and implementation details of an SPL are
described in the level of classes. There is a gap between existing
approaches and existing practical needs. In this work, we extend
the current state of the art to deal with feature modularization in
the level of classes by introducing a new search operator and a set
of objective functions to deal with feature modularization in a finer
granularity of the architectural elements, namely at class level. We
evaluated the proposal in an exploratory study with a PLA widely
investigated and a real-world PLA. The results of quantitative and
qualitative analysis point out that our proposal provides solutions
to properly re-modularize features in a PLA, being preferred by
practitioners, in order to support the evolution of SPLs.</abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ZSQRgdvblb-68hPo4SS7fB8R-JDLhtba/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
  </work>
   <work>
    <year>2020</year>
    <title>OPLA-Tool v2.0: a Tool for Product Line Architecture Design Optimization</title>
    <author>Willian Marques Freire</author>
    <photo>https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/g_B2ljx1CGJvAQ96D-L1LAUplixJCSZWd3VEZfNIia2Q-rD39ZGqVH7YVwE1rMJELD_8vbv4hj8feSlE42A=w1848-h981-rw</photo>
    <git>http://github.com/wmfsystem</git>
    <abstract>The Multi-objective Optimization Approach for Product Line Architecture Design (MOA4PLA) 
      is the seminal approach that successfully optimizes Product Line Architecture (PLA) design using 
      search algorithms. The tool named OPLA-Tool was developed in order to automate the use of MOA4PLA. 
      Over time, the customization of the tool to suit the needs of new research and application scenarios 
      led to several problems. The main problems identified in the original version of OPLA-Tool are environment 
      configuration, maintainability and usability problems, and PLA design modeling and visualization.
      Such problems motivated the development of a new version of this tool: OPLA-Tool v2.0, presented in this work.
      In this version, those problems were solved by the source code refactoring, migration to a web-based graphical
      user interface (GUI) and inclusion of a new support tool for PLA modeling and visualization. Furthermore, 
      OPLA-Tool v2.0 has new functionalities, such as new objective functions, new search operators, intelligent 
      interaction with users during the optimization process, multi-user authentication and simultaneous execution
      of several experiments to PLA optimization. Such a new version of OPLA-Tool is an important achievement to PLA design optimization as it provides an easier and more complete way to automate this task. </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1b3gQ59s1YWRLQ1zxwGCuMPqLubmv0BeJ/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
  </work>
   <work>
    <year>2020</year>
    <title>Supporting user preferences in search-based product line architecture design using Machine Learning</title>
    <author>Carlos Vinicius Bindewald</author>
    <abstract>The Product Line Architecture (PLA) is one of the most important artifacts of a Software Product Line. 
      PLA design requires intensive human effort as it involves several conflicting factors. In order to support this 
      task, an interactive search-based approach, automated by a tool named OPLA-Tool, was proposed in a previous work. 
      Through this tool the software architect evaluates the generated solutions during the optimization process. 
      Considering that evaluating PLA is a complex task and search-based algorithms demand a high number of generations, 
      the evaluation of all solutions in all generations cause human fatigue. In this work, we incorporated in OPLA-Tool 
      a Machine Learning (ML) model to represent the architect in some moments during the optimization process aiming 
      to decrease the architect's effort. Through the execution of a quanti-qualitative exploratory study it was possible
      to demonstrate the reduction of the fatigue problem and that the solutions produced at the end of the process, in 
      most cases, met the architect’s needs.</abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1YFyAqUD7Gh32Z5FD5RzgeywH0EJWQLzR/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink>https://github.com/otimizes/experimental-package-interactive-vin</experimentalpackagelink>
  </work>
  <work>
    <year>2019</year>
    <title>Supporting decision makers in search-based product line architecture design using clustering</title>
    <author>Willian Marques Freire</author>
    <photo>https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/g_B2ljx1CGJvAQ96D-L1LAUplixJCSZWd3VEZfNIia2Q-rD39ZGqVH7YVwE1rMJELD_8vbv4hj8feSlE42A=w1848-h981-rw</photo>
    <git>http://github.com/wmfsystem</git>
    <abstract>The Product Line Architecture (PLA) is one of the most important artifacts of a Software Product Line (SPL). 
    PLA design can be formulated as an optimization problem with many factors. In this context, the MOA4PLA approach was 
    proposed to optimize PLA design using search algorithms and metrics specific to the context. 
    MOA4PLA treats the PLA design as a multi-objective optimization problem. At the end of the search process several PLA design 
    alternatives are presented to the decision maker, difficulting the decision about which PLA alternative best fits with 
    his/her needs. In this sense, this work proposes the usage of clustering algorithms to group PLAs design alternatives, 
    according to their characteristics and assist the decision maker in the choice of one PLA design for the SPL. 
    For this purpose, an empirical study was carried out, involving quantitative and qualitative experiments. 
    Such an study integrated the K-Means++ and DBSCAN clustering algorithms in the MOA4PLA approach. 
    The results of the experiments were promising, since an appropriate grouping of the solutions can be quantitatively observed, 
    and also, qualitatively, the suitability of the solutions to the decision makers needs was verified.</abstract>
    <paperlink>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8754394</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink>https://github.com/wmfsubmissions/experimental-packages-compsac.git</experimentalpackagelink>
  </work>
  <work>
    <year>2019</year>
    <title>Towards the support of user preferences in search-based product line architecture design: an exploratory study</title>
    <author>Carlos Vinicius Bindewald</author>
    <abstract>Software Product Lines (SPLs) is a reuse approach in which a family of products is generalized in a 
    common architecture that can be adapted to different clients. The Product Line Architecture (PLA) is one of 
    the most important artifacts of a SPL. PLA design requires great human effort as it involves several factors 
    that are usually in conflict. To ease this task, PLA design can be formulated as an optimization problem with 
    many factors, i.e, as a multi-objective optimization problem. In this context, the MOA4PLA approach was proposed 
    to optimize PLA design using search algorithms and metrics specific to the context. This approach supported by 
    OPLA-Tool has already been used in several works demonstrating its applicability. However, MOA4PLA does not take 
    into account aspects that are subjective, such as the preferences of a particular Decision Maker (DM). To do so, 
    this paper presents a proposal to incorporate the user preferences in the optimization process performed by MOA4PLA,
    through an interactive process in which the DM subjectively evaluates the solutions in processing time. Thus, 
    the solutions generated can be better suited to the DM's needs or preferences. In order to allow the user interaction, 
    modifications were made in MOA4PLA and implemented in the OPLA-Tool. Aiming at an initial validation of the proposal, 
    an exploratory study was carried out, composed of two experiments: a qualitative and a quantitative. These experiments
    were realized with the participation of a software architect. Empirical results pointed out that the proposed interactive
    process enables the generation of PLAs that are in accordance with the architect's preferences. 
    Another significant contribution are the lessons learned on how to improve the interactive process.</abstract>
    <paperlink>https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3351993</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink>https://mega.nz/##!cTISxaiQ!YSrv3TuK6OKD41dVO7bSp_wx2heZOUxjBNtyHsAXlAo</experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2017</year>
    <title>A Approach to Optimize Software Product Line Design</title>
    <author>João Choma Neto</author>
    <abstract>
    This work is focused on the application of memetic algorithms in the Software Product
Line (SPL) architecture design. Product Line Architecture (PLA) is one of the most
important SPL artifacts since it contains all the information needed to generate SPL
products. Building a PLA design is a difficult and highly architect-dependent activity.
PLA design could be modeled as an optimization problem to be solved by Search
Based Software Engineering (SBSE). SBSE aims at automatically obtaining near-optimal
solutions using multi-objective search algorithms. In this context, MOA4PLA approach
was developed in order to optimize PLA design in terms of basic design principles, feature
modularization and SPL extensibility, with the use of multi-objective search algorithms.
OPLA-Tool automates MOA4PLA by using multi-objective search algorithms based on
genetic algorithms (GA). In this tool there is a module called OPLA-Patterns responsible
for applying design patterns during the optimization process. According to the systematic
mapping performed, the memetic algorithms (MA), which consist of the use of GAs
with local search, have achieved better results in optimization problems when compared
with GA. However, there were no report on the use of memetic algorithms for PLA
design optimization. Thus, this work deals with the application of AMs to optimize
PLA design, adapting the search operator named Design Pattern Mutation Operator
proposed in OPLA-Patterns as a local search operator. Four distinct versions of AM were
implemented, each one with a different selection criterion. Empirical studies were carried
out to compared the solutions obtained by both GA and four versions of MA through
quantitative and qualitative analysis. In general, the quantitative studies indicated that
the AM found better solutions in terms of fitness when compared with GA. The qualitative
study pointed out that the solutions obtained with AM, in the context of MOA4PLA, are
good from the software architects point of view. The AM still needs to be refined with
improvements identified during the steps of this work.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1y0RdTVWh9nH9n0YzjYPg84k8olO1ZyC1/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2017</year>
    <title>Expansion of an evaluation model of software product line architecture</title>
    <author>Yenisei Delgado Verdecia</author>
    <abstract>
    The primary purpose of a Software Product Line (LPS) is to reduce costs and increase
productivity by reusing artifacts. In this approach, the main artifact is the Product
Line Architecture (PLA) because it provides a solution for a range of LPS products.
Evaluating the PLA design is a fundamental and complex task during the LPS life cycle,
since the PLA specifies a set of reusable components in the LPS. The search for solutions to
software engineering problems has been addressed in the search field called Search- based
Software Engineering (SBSE) through approaches based on Multi-Objective Evolutionary
Algorithms (MOEAs), which consider different factors and measures that affect the
PLA design problem. In order to evaluate PLA designs, which use different software
metrics to evaluate the modularity of characteristics, the PLA extensibility and the basic
principles of design, the Multi-Objective Approach for Product Line Architecture Design
(MOA4PLA) was proposed. However, other architectural properties can be evaluated. In
this context, the objective of the present work was to expand the MOA4PLA evaluation
model with metrics that assess other PLA design properties. Therefore, a quality model
was defined for the MOA4PLA. After, other metrics have been identified to measure
other architectural properties in the proposed quality model. Taking into account the
new selected metrics, new objective functions were defined in the MOA4PLA evaluation
model and implemented in the tool OPLA-tool. In order to investigate the correlation
between the new objective functions, an exploratory study was carried out involving four
experiments. Thus, the present work expands the evaluation model of the MOA4PLA,
with other metrics to evaluate PLA designs. The main contributions of this work are: the
proposal of the quality model for SBPD, the use of metrics for LPS oriented to services
applied for the first time in the context of SBPD; and the new objective functions that
let evaluate other architectural properties in the evaluation model of MOA4PLA.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1l4M7Gnr0YZaarUbquebR_b0AAC2lBCch/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2015</year>
    <title>Preservating the architectural style in the software product line design</title>
    <author>Thainá Mariani</author>
    <abstract>
    The adoption of architectural styles helps to improve the Product Line Architecture (PLA)
design by providing a better organization of the elements, flexibility, extensibility and
maintainability. Search based optimization approaches can also benefit the PLA design,
by generating PLA alternatives associated the best trade-offs between different measures
related to cohesion, coupling and feature modularization. However, the usage of existing
search operators changes the PLA organization, and consequently may violate styles rules,
impacting negatively the architecture understanding. In order to solve this problem,
this work introduces a set of search operators, named SO4ARS (Search Operators for
preserving Architectural Styles), which considers rules of the main architectural styles,
generally used in the search based design of conventional architectures and PLAs: layered,
client/server and aspect-oriented styles. The search operators were implemented in the
OPLA-ArchStyles module and integrated to OPLA-Tool, which supports the use of the
Multi-objective Optimization Approach for PLA Design (MOA4PLA) in order to help the
search based design of PLAs. Results from an empirical evaluation show that the proposed
operators contribute to obtain better solutions, by maintaining the adopted style and also
improving some software metrics values.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1mQz5C6m-ZPTnJd8nzMBsdSendWlKZsx4/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2016</year>
    <title>An evaluation model to Search-based ALPS design</title>
    <author>Marcelo Carlos Benitez dos Santos</author>
    <abstract>
    The Product Line Architecture (ALP) is considered the most important artifact in
a Software Product Line (LPS), as it includes a joint design to every LPS product.
Thus, evaluate and modularize the ALP is essential to get a good LPS design. However,
evaluation and modularization of ALP activities are difficult and require great human
effort without the aid of an automated tool. It can be easy for an architect to recognize a
good ALP design, however, it is difficult to get it. Therefore, MOA4PLA (Multi-Objective
Approach for Product-Line Architecture Design), was proposed, which has the purpose to
help the architect to evaluate and improve ALP design. This approach is multi-objective
and uses an evaluation model composede by evaluation function to assess the ALP design.
These functions are based on different metrics, which involve different architectural pro-
perties. Currently, the evaluation model presents problems in some evaluation functions,
because these functions evaluate the desingn utilizing metrics with different magnitudes,
so that the information resultant of the assessment is provided in a more general way. This
work therefore proposes to restructure the evaluation model of MOA4PLA, separating
the CM (pla) and FM (pla) by its architectural properties, generating new evaluation
functions and increasing optimization options. Experimental studies were performed to
investigate a possible correlation between the new evaluation functions. The results show
that most of the functions are negatively correlated, so that when one function increases
the other decreases. Thus the function has to be selected as an objective, if the architect
wants to prioritize it in the optimization process.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/16mdgNKEfw36Q41HU6GJ30ItR0JaeRZc8/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2014</year>
    <title>Use of patterns on Search-based software product line architecture design</title>
    <author>Giovani Guizzo</author>
    <abstract>
    Design patterns aim at improving the understanding and reuse of software architectures.
In the search-based design they have been successfully applied by mutation operators in
the evolutionary process. In the software Product Line Architecture (PLA) context, some
works have manually applied design patterns, but there are no search-based approaches
that take into account the use of these patterns. To make this use possible is the goal
of this work, which introduces an automated way for the application of design patterns
through a mutation operator in the MOA4PLA approach (Multi-objective Optimization
Approach for PLA Design). The goal is to avoid the introduction of architectural ano-
malies and to ensure that these patterns are applied only in feasible scopes. To this
end, a feasibility analysis was conducted to determine which patterns of the GoF (Gang
of Four ) catalog could be applied in the context of MOA4PLA. A mutation operator
is proposed in order to apply feasible design patterns in PLAs during the evolutionary
process. The operator uses scope verification and design patterns application methods.
The mutation operator was implemented in the OPLA-Patterns module of OPLA-Tool,
which supports the MOA4PLA approach. Experiments were configured and executed in
real PLAs to quantitatively and qualitatively evaluate the results. The results showed
that the application of design patterns allows the generation of architectures with better
values of the software metrics. A greater diversity of solutions was obtained, then the
architect can choose which one best fits his/her objectives. Therefore, the application of
design patterns using the proposed operator contributes positively to the PLA design.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Y9C9mdg1lwOhoNM0viW9HzWg9JqhE_ot/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2014</year>
    <title>A tool to assist the search-based software product line architecture design</title>
    <author>Édipo Luis Féderle</author>
    <abstract>
    The design of Product Line Architecture (PLA) is a complex task, which is influenced
by several factors, such as feature modularization and PLA extensibility. Such factors are
often evaluated according to different types of metrics. Thus, the PLA design can be seen
as an optimization problem. This category of problem has been successfully solved in the
research field named Search Based Software Engineering (SBSE) that uses metaheuristics,
such as Genetic Algorithms. In this context, Colanzi [16] proposed an approach named
Multi-Objective Approach for Product-Line Architecture Design (MOA4PLA), to be sup-
ported by a tool named OPLA-Tool (Optimization for PLA Tool). This tool is composed
by different modules and only one of these modules has been implemented in [16]. This
work implements three essential modules of OPLA-Tool, which offer automated support
to allow the use of MOA4PLA in practice: OPLA-Encoding, OPLA-Decoding and OPLA-
GUI. Such modules provide features that automate many tasks of MOA4PLA approach,
such as reading and instantiation of a PLA in memory, generation of solutions in order to
be possible their visualization, and a graphical interface, making the use of MOA4PLA
more productive. The implementation and integration of such modules were evaluated
using real PLAs. The obtained results show the usefulness of OPLA-Tool, which contri-
butes to reduce the effort spent in the PLA design and improvement.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1UIOdnHswYn86Z0Kw3VgJiD_bL_j73MxF/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2015</year>
    <title>Search operator adaptations for software product line architecture design optimization</title>
    <author>Thais Santos Nepomuceno</author>
    <abstract>
    Software Product Line aims reuse and decrease development costs. One of the main
generated artifacts is The Product Line Architecture (PLA). The PLA Project can be
formulated as a multi-objective optimization problem. So an automated optimization approach
can be used, the Multi Objective Approach for Product Line Architecture Design,
MOA4PLA, which aims to optimize an architecture in terms of basic design principles,
modularization LPS features and extensibility. The OPLA-Tool allows the application of this
approach. However, this approach needs improvement since the PLAs generated have some
problems like interfaces and classes isolated in the project. According to previous studies, this
may be related to some of the MOA4PLA search operators are: Operation Move, Add
Component and Feature-driven Operator. Thus, the objective of this work is to make the
necessary changes in operators in OPLA-Tool aiming to solve such problems and determine if
they were resolved by experiments and analyzes in PLAs generated. These solutions were not
as expected, the class and interfaces isolates issue, which also cause isolated package still
exists. In addition, other problems were identified in OPLA-Tool.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1tS7NCLGVqxIWMwpizJ7v2iUAEAAa2VL4/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2017</year>
    <title>NSGA-III Algorithm Implementation for Product Line Design Optimization</title>
    <author>Pedro Barbiero</author>
    <abstract>
    Software Product Line (SPL) is a software reuse method shown to reduce the cost of software
production over time. The reuse occurs through a Product Line Architecture (PLA), where the
architecture of each SPL product is derived from a PLA. The structure of a PLA may be repre-
sented through a class diagram. Software metrics can be defined to evaluate several properties
of the architectural project. Some of these metrics may conflict. Within this context, the PLA
project can be modeled as a multi-objective optimization problem. This is the main objective
for the Multi-objective Optimization Approach for PLA Design (MOA4PLA), which defined
17 objective functions for PLA evaluation. These functions are derived or composed by one or
more software metrics, such that software architect can choose a subset of these functions for
the optimization process. This approach may use different optimization algorithms to realize
its process. It has been implemented by the open source software OPLA-Tool. This software
uses the NSGA-II algorithm for its multiobjective optimization. When increasing the number
of objective functions in its evaluation model, it’s possible to observe an increase of execution
time. In this context, this tool implemented another algorithm, the NSGA-III, with the goal
of comparing the performance and results generated by it. Experiments comparing both algo-
rithms were executed, with evaluation models of two, three and five objectives. It was noted
that, within the context of this work, NSGA-III created a solution set of better quality than the
NSGA-II. Future study cases for improving the OPLA-Tool were also noted.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1j3pK7KcvdONeyh8UvvJF5j8-rT3hJA6k/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2016</year>
    <title>Search based design evaluation for software product line architecture</title>
    <author>Guilherme Conte Dias</author>
    <abstract>
    Software Product Line (LPS) is an approach that allows exploring the similarities among its
products, in order to promote the reuse of the artifacts involved, directly reducing the cost and
the development time of a project. In this approach, the main artifact is the Produtc Line
Architecture (PLA). Architectural metrics support architects to define and improve a PLA in
order to be cohesive, modular and reusable. However, metrics can be inconflict. When this
problem happens architects must choose which metric should be prioritized, what is not a
simple task, as there is not always an optimal and exact solution. Considering this fact,
Colanzi (2014) introduced the MOA4PLA approach (Multi-Objective Approach to Product
Line Architecture) which aims at optimizing PLAs. To allow an automation of the
MOA4PLA approach, Colanzi (2014) proposed a tool called OPLA-Tool (Optimization for
PLA Tool). This work consists in the accomplishment of a qualitative evaluation of the results
generated by this tool. Specialists in the area of Software Engineering evaluated some PLA
designs generated by OPLA-Tool. The results obtained from the qualitative analysis based on
the feedback of the specialists allowed to identify that, as PLAs obtained are consistent with
the objectives that were optimized and that the architectural characteristics that the experts are
judgments are just like that were evaluated in this study.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wzjnsmMNF08DapFakR9kSshKvMUPLHFl/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2017</year>
    <title>Identification of architectural anomalies in software product line design</title>
    <author>Eduardo Germano Perissatto</author>
    <abstract>
    In the Software Product Line (SPL) approach is developed a family of products for a given
domain. One of the main artifacts generated is the Product Line Architecture (PLA), which
contains the common design to all SPL derivable products. In order for an PLA to be cost-
effective it is necessary for the components of the PLA to be modularized, which is not trivial
to obtain due to several – possibly conflicting – factors to consider. Considering this problem
of optimization of PLA projects, it was proposed the Multi-Objective Approach for Product-
Line Architecture (MOA4PLA), whose automation was done through the OPLA-Tool, which
generates new solutions from a given initial solution (the original PLA design). However,
these solutions have the drawback of presenting architectural smells, which are problems at
the software architecture level that negatively affect their quality. This work consisted of an
analysis of several PLAs, aiming to find architectural smells. The results were evaluated to
verify the influence of OPLA-Tool on the types of anomalies present in the generated
solutions, in contrast to the types of anomalies previously existing in the original solutions.
Finally, guidelines were proposed to detect and remove the types of anomalies found.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1FPfGUknBxRbNKEPyHqCfN7F6_yD5r8h_/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2018</year>
    <title>OPLA-Tool Technology Acceptance Assessment</title>
    <author>Marcos Brunelli Francisco</author>
    <abstract>
    When performing a heuristic evaluation in a software system, focusing on its usability, it is
possible to raise several improvements that can be applied to this, aiming to improve their
human-computer interaction. Given the improvements applied to a software, its acceptance by
its possible users can be evaluated, so that they are able to measure the acceptability of this
software from the results obtained from this evaluation. One of these resources is the
Technology Acceptance Model, which provides a way to evaluate a technology according to
pre-established variables. Within the context presented, this work proposes the
implementation of changes in the OPLA-Tool tool interface, a software capable of producing
optimized alternatives for the design of product line architectures. These changes were
suggestions, presented in a previous work, in which a heuristic evaluation was performed
focusing on the usability of this tool. With the modifications applied, an experiment was
carried out with end users, in which a software implementation scenario was proposed. From
this, a questionnaire was built based on the Technology Acceptance Model and with the data
obtained, it was possible to measure the acceptability of the OPLA-Tool by the participants of
this experiment. From the accomplishment of such activities, it was possible to infer that the
tool was accepted by these participants, being possible to analyze some of its positive and
negative points.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1MzEg04QWnfCJHMSlASgQsVZO-u25qhYU/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2018</year>
    <title>Evaluation and proposal of improvement of interaction in the OPLA-Tool through the application of Nielsen Usability Heuristics</title>
    <author>Hadyne Cristine Biazoto</author>
    <abstract>
    At first, only highly trained users were able to use a computer. Nowadays
this scenario has changed and many people, even without experience, use these
machines. With this, it is necessary to develop an interface that is easy to use.
Otherwise, if it is not properly developed, it may compromise the user's use of the
software. Since the OPLA - Tool was developed with an initial focus on functional
requirements, there was no study and study of usability heuristics. The objective
of this work is to evaluate the tool according to the 10 heuristics of Nielsen and
to propose improvements for its interface. After this analysis and answering the
questionnaire, which is in Annex A, some usability problems were found in the
tool interface. For these cases, prototypes were made with the proposed
improvements to the OPLA - Tool.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1WDPzLgx_sr9Fz6DVCAmu1IxS_xPchQSC/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2015</year>
    <title>Prioritizing features to be modularized in product line architecture</title>
    <author>Diego Fernandes da Silva</author>
    <abstract>
    One of main Software Product Line's (SPL) artifacts, which is an approach for the
development of software applications in large scale, is the Product-Line Architecture
(PLA). The MOA4PLA approach includes one searching operator for improving PLA
projects in relation to features modularization through small modifications in a PLA
project. However, this searching operator of the related approach do not prioritize
features to be modularized. Thereby, all the features are modularized with the same
ratio of probability. However, it is customary hold a list of the prioritized features
involved in the SPL's products that will be derived or evolved. These features should
have modularization's priority. In this context, this paper aims to perform necessary
modifications in the OPLA-Tool, in which automates the application of the MOA4PLA
approach, in order to allow the SPL features prioritization. Two methods to prioritize
modularization's features are proposed: One in which the user select a order of features
to be prioritized and another in which the features are prioritized automatically
according to the feature's type. Only the first method was implemented due to the long
time spent to compile OPLA-tool. After its implementation, an experiment was
conducted using one PLA and prioritizing some features. The results showed
improvement in modularization of prioritized features.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1116TnpxBeS9_qRIBnIRnpB6u12RtWDj9/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2017</year>
    <title>Study and policy setting for research group software configuration management</title>
    <author>Felipe Fernandes da Silva</author>
    <abstract>
    In the software development there may be inadequate management of artifacts when it is
necessary that several people act making major changes. Configuration management acts
to facilitate collaborative development, but the proposed models do not meet the specific
demands that may arise within software development teams. An example is the research group
development environment in which the roles and tasks proposed by existing configuration
management models do not correspond to reality. Therefore, this work aims to show the
existing proposals of configuration management for software development through theoretical
research, demonstrating the main concepts of each aspect of this process, in order to create a
configuration management model that meets the environment of research groups, adapting
roles and simplifying tasks so that software development within these groups occurs in the
most orderly way possible.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1UcoWo8Pfv5hiefsCURHtZvThfdf77Q1i/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
   <work>
    <year>2015</year>
    <title>Prioritizing features to be modularized in product line architecture</title>
    <author>Diego Fernandes da Silva</author>
    <abstract>
    One of main Software Product Line's (SPL) artifacts, which is an approach for the
development of software applications in large scale, is the Product-Line Architecture
(PLA). The MOA4PLA approach includes one searching operator for improving PLA
projects in relation to features modularization through small modifications in a PLA
project. However, this searching operator of the related approach do not prioritize
features to be modularized. Thereby, all the features are modularized with the same
ratio of probability. However, it is customary hold a list of the prioritized features
involved in the SPL's products that will be derived or evolved. These features should
have modularization's priority. In this context, this paper aims to perform necessary
modifications in the OPLA-Tool, in which automates the application of the MOA4PLA
approach, in order to allow the SPL features prioritization. Two methods to prioritize
modularization's features are proposed: One in which the user select a order of features
to be prioritized and another in which the features are prioritized automatically
according to the feature's type. Only the first method was implemented due to the long
time spent to compile OPLA-tool. After its implementation, an experiment was
conducted using one PLA and prioritizing some features. The results showed
improvement in modularization of prioritized features.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1116TnpxBeS9_qRIBnIRnpB6u12RtWDj9/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink></experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
  <work>
    <year>2017</year>
    <title>Qualitative Analysis of Software Product Line Architecture optimized from the OPLA-Tool</title>
    <author>Thiago de Oliveira Lavezzo</author>
    <abstract>
    Software Product Line (LPS) is a collection of systems that share characteristics in a managed way through 
       its various artifacts. It aims to increase software reuse, decrease production time and product development 
       costs. In this approach, the main artifact is the LPS architecture (PLA - Product Line Architecture). 
       Architectural metrics support architects to define and improve a PLA so that it is cohesive, modular and 
       reusable. However, this task can involve several factors, which can often conflict with each other. 
       When this occurs, architects must choose which ones to prioritize, this is not a simple task and requires 
       great human effort, as there is not always an optimal and exact solution. In this context, Colanzi (2014)
       introduced the MOA4PLA (Multi-Objective Approach for Product-Line Architecture) approach that aims to optimize 
       PLAs. To allow the automation of the MOA4PLA approach, Colanzi (2014) proposed a tool called OPLA-Tool 
       (Optimization for PLA Tool). This work consisted of a qualitative analysis of PLAs optimized from the OPLA-Tool. 
       The results were obtained from the analysis of these PLAs by specialists in the area of Software Engineering. 
       The results obtained from the qualitative analysis based on the experts' feedback, showed positive and negative 
       points of the optimized PLAs, being that in general they were consistent with what was optimized in the project.
    </abstract>
    <paperlink>https://drive.google.com/file/d/18VvybfXxo-Me3suWHFLFSGmE3qp8zCGB/view?usp=sharing</paperlink>
    <experimentalpackagelink>https://github.com/otimizes/experimental-package-quali-optimized-pla</experimentalpackagelink>
  </work> 
</works>
